Hello friends, my name is Anil Rajput.
I am the founder of Family First Financial
Services. I am an MBA Finance and have been
working in the corporate sector for 13 years and
today I am presenting before you the best
health insurance plans in India in 2023-24 based on the best features. Their
comparison is Niva Bappa Yo 2.8 Care Health
Insurance's Care Supreme product and
HDFC Gogo Health Insurance's Optima
Secure plan. I have compared all these three best plans. I have made
individual videos of all these three plans. There are
many features which I have compared
for you, so watch this video completely
and if you like the video then watch my
YouTube channel to compare the features in detail. The
first feature is called
Lock the Clock feature. This is the same in both Rish 2.0
Gold and Platinum. Gold has
just been launched recently which is the
same feature as Platinum, so this Lock the
Clock feature is available in it. This option is not available in Health Care Supreme
and Optima Secure, HDFC and Care.
Lock the
Clock at all.  How it works is that as
your age increases, the
health insurance company
increases your premium after every 5 years, but if
you do not make any claim in this policy, then
your premium will not increase, even if
you are 35 years old or 50 years old, if you never
make a claim, the premium will never
increase, so what will be its benefits, how does
it work, let us first understand this,
now taking an example, there is a person
whose age is 45 years, his wife is 44 years old
and he has a son who is 11 years old and a
daughter who is 8 years old and they are
purchasing the policy on 25th November 2023, that is today
when I am making this video and at
that time the premium of RIS 2.0 Gold plan is Rs.
26400.76, premium is of Rs. 10 lakh and
insurance cover is Rs. 10 lakh, I have kept Zone 1,
now because in this plan we assume
that the customer has not made any claim,
he has turned 35 years old, sorry, 45 years old
and there is no claim. Next year on 25th
November 2024 when he turns 46 and has
not made any claim, then in Rio 2.0
your premium will be 2476.
Your premium will not increase by ₹1 due to the lock the
clock feature. But suppose if you had
purchased this policy as Supreme,
your premium would have been ₹358. Here
I have added community bonus, annual
health checkup, wellness benefit and air
ambulance
because all these features are under NB and
in Care, all these are optional. So optional,
many times when you read the browser,
many features look similar,
but one is inbuilt and one is optional.
For inbuilt, you do
not have to pay a separate premium for it, for optional,
you have to pay a separate premium. So,
I have taken these together from the point of view of comparison
that if we compare with the same features,
what will be the benefits?
So the premium of Care Supreme will be
2735 will come when the customer turns 45, that is, at
this time on November 25, 2023, when he takes the policy,
his claim also did not come, but because
his age increased from 45 to 46 on
November 25, 2024, then his renewal premium next year will be
37911 because the age has increased, but
due to lock the clock in Niva, the
premium remained 2647 only. In ADAC, your 45 case
premium is 3896 and in 36-46 case the
premium will be 4160, so lock the
clock is very beneficial for you. If you are taking
care of your health and fall sick less often, then
this feature will be very useful for you.
Now let us look at the
second feature which is called Restoration of
Cover. Restoration is called Riser For Ever in Niva Bupa
and Unlimited Restoration Recharge
in Care Supreme and it is known as Restore
Benefit in Optima Secure.
Different names have been given
but it remains restored. Restoration means
that suppose you have an
insurance cover of Rs 10 lakh and a claim of Rs
10 lakh has come, then the
company will restore it and give you a cover of Rs 10 lakh again. There will be
no separate premium for this,
it comes inbuilt, so you can
claim Rs 20 lakh in the entire year, for example, if it
is unlimited, then you can claim Rs 10 lakh as many
times as you want. Now here
you will see another unique feature
in this Niva Bap, now first let me
tell you a little about how the registration cover remains, first of all, you will
see that here you will see
that unlimited times in a year for both
related and unrelated illnesses, this will be carried
forward at the time of every renewal, first of all, the
insurance cover that you have, this
restoration benefit is
available even if the same illness happens to the same person,
what happens in many insurance policies is that
Restoration benefit is not covered in the same person with the same disease, but here
it will cover the same person with the same disease as well and
it is also carried forward. Now I will
explain it in detail a little later. Riser For Ever has
a unique benefit in it that it has to be
triggered only once in a lifetime. Only
once means once you have a
claim, say after two years or
after four years, then it will be activated for you.
Then whenever there is a claim more than your basic insurance
cover,
you can avail the restore benefit,
suppose your basic cover was 10 lakhs, 10
lakhs has been fully utilized, then you are
getting the restoration benefit and you are
using it continuously. But
in other companies like Care Insurance and Optima Secure, you will
not get this benefit there for life time. It will have to be
triggered every year, that is,
suppose your claim came this year and got triggered, and the
claim comes again next year, then the
trigger will have to be first and then the second.  You will get
benefit in claim or else you will not
get it, how do you understand,
like for
example, I am taking an example
that the same person has taken insurance cover of Rs 10 lakh from all the
three companies, suppose there are
three different persons, same judge and each has been
given a cover of Rs 10 lakh,
they have purchased the policy in 2023 and next year
their claim came for Rs 10 lakh, all the three
companies will provide them a claim of Rs 10 lakh,
now look at the insurance of all three here,
this February restore has been
triggered for life time,
now suppose next year in 2025, after 2 years, a
claim of Rs 20 lakh comes together, the
first claim came for Rs 20 lakh in 2025, then the
company will give you 10 lakh basic cover and 10 lakh restoration benefit, total 20 lakh
because your restore got activated in 2024,
but your care Supreme N
Optima  They will say no, we will give you only 10 lakhs,
your claim has not been activated yet,
first it will have to be activated, whether it is with a
claim of 50,000 or 5 lakhs,
then when the second claim comes in 2025,
then we will give you the restore benefit.
I have tried to explain the restore here.
Here I have just kept the no claim
bonus aside,
how the restore exactly works,
once it is triggered, then
restore and lock the clock, both
are great features for you under NB. Actually, the
features of all the three companies are good, actually, but
how can it be better in these, that is what I am
trying to explain to you.
In ADFC Gogo, you will get the restore benefit only
once, it will not be available unlimited times.
If you want to avail it unlimited times, then
you will have to take Edge Addon for which you will have to pay a
premium of Rs. 10 lakh.
Another benefit in NBPA is that as
your insurance cover
increases, I will start increasing the cost from here.  Let me explain, let us
see the
next feature here which is called No Claim
Bonus. In simple language, people understand No Claim Bonus.
Here, No Claim Bonus is
described as Boor Plus in Niva Bupa.
In Care, it is
described as Cumulate Bonus. In HDFC Rugo, it is
known as Plus Benefit. Meaning, it
works just like No Claim Bonus. For example, if
I talk about Care, there is a cumulative bonus, it will be
given at 50% on 50%, that is, if
you have an insurance of Rs. 10 lakh, if there is
no claim next year, it will increase by 50%. Even if there is a
claim, it will increase and then next year it will
increase by another %, that is, 50%. Your
insurance cover will increase by 50% in the next two years. So,
after two years, your cover of Rs. 10 lakh will increase to Rs. 20 lakh. And this will remain
inbuilt. But if you
want to increase the insurance cover further with time, then
you will have to take a Community Bonus Super.
It will be optional for which you will have to
pay an additional premium. So, your
insurance will increase by Rs. 500.  It will happen
that the additional amount of 10 lakh will increase to 50 lakh i.e. if you
took a cover of 10 lakh, in
front of the cover of 10 lakh, your cumulative
bonus will increase to 55 lakh and 50 lakh every
year 10 lakh 10 lakh 10 lakh 10 lakh 10 lakh
so the total insurance cover will be
70 lakh after 7 years, even if a
claim of up to 70 lakh comes at one go, the company will still give it to you, the
good thing is in the care supreme that whether
your claim is coming or not, now the
full ₹ lakh that you are getting, there will be no
difference in it, you will definitely get it,
okay plus benefit, if I
talk about HDFC Optima Secure, then
here
you will get 50 lakh next year and the next
year also you will get 50 lakh i.e. 55 lakh, so
after two years your insurance cover will
increase to 20 lakh for you, whether a
claim comes here or not, it does not matter,
your insurance cover will definitely
increase here  If you look at Niva Bapa Resource 2.2
Gold or Platinum, the
insurance cover here is inbuilt,
you do not have to pay a separate premium for this, the
insurance will increase five times, that is, the
insurance cover of 10 lakhs will now be added by 50 lakhs, making the
total 60 lakhs, and
restoration benefits will come separately, they are there
in all three plans, so you can utilize that too, so
this no claim bonus is for you,
now the secure benefit, secure benefit
means that it is
available only in ADFC, sorry, I am
writing in ADFC, here in the picture, please make sure
that instead of A, it is
in ADFC, in Niv and Care, this option is
not there, so secure benefit
is only in ADFC and is in ADFC Optima Secure,
this means that
from the very first day, you will
get double the insurance that you purchase, that is, if you take an insurance cover of 10 lakhs, then
you will get 10 lakhs for free, that is, in the
first year itself, if you
Suppose you fall sick after two months and a
claim of 20 lakhs comes in at once, STFC
Rugo will pay you the entire claim of 20 lakhs.
This is under HDFC Rugo, sorry, it has been
typed wrongly here, so
convert it into SDFC Rugo.
This feature is not in Niva Bappa. Let us
see the next feature,
which is Ko Payment Ko Payment. Let me go back a little and
explain to you
that this 5x no claim bonus that you are getting
under Niva Bappa, this is
also carried forward. Suppose for
example, in 3 years your insurance cover
increases to 30 lakhs. 10 lakhs is your
basic insurance cover and it has become 40 lakhs.
Now your claim of 20 lakhs comes in at once, so the
company pays you 20 lakhs. The
remaining 20 lakhs will be carried forward to the next year. So,
next year also, when
you get a new insurance cover of 10 lakhs and 20
lakhs of the old one, then the total is 30 lakhs.  If this happens, then
even next year if a claim of Rs 30 lakh
comes in simultaneously, the insurance company will pay Rs 10 lakh and you are already getting the restore benefit
separately.
Now let's see, co-payment
means
that the customer also pays a certain
percentage. Suppose co-payment is done
at 10% here, then the
customer will pay Rs 10% of the final bill of the claim and the
company will pay Rs 90%. But here it is
written 'Fully Paid by Insurance',
which means that no one is paying you from your pocket, the
company will pay the entire amount. There is
no co-payment in all three plans, which is
excellent. Talking about pre-hospitalization,
before getting admitted to the hospital,
like you got the diagnosis test done,
took medicine, incurred expenses in doctor consultation,
then felt that you were
not getting well, so got admitted to the hospital, then
you will
get the expenses of 60 days before admission and 180 days after discharge, that is, the first two months and the remaining 6 months, in both these three policies.  Under pre-hospitalization
and hospitalization expenses, let's
talk about day care treatment. Day care
treatment means that
you don't have to be admitted for 24 hours. So,
in all three policies, all three
plans cover all day care procedures. There is
no limit on the
cover for 541, 248, or 250 days.
Here, all day care
treatments will be covered. Hospitalization at
home. Sometimes, what happens is, for example,
in a situation like Covid, there are no beds available in the hospital, there is
no vacant space, or the
patient is so ill that it is
difficult to transport him from home to the hospital.
In those cases,
you can get treatment at home up to the amount of your insurance cover.
Talking about ambulance charges,
you can avail road ambulance benefit up to the
amount of your insurance cover in Niva Bappa.
Talking about Kate Supreme, if your
insurance cover is less than Rs 15 lakh, you
can avail road ambulance benefit up to Rs 10,000.  And if your insurance cover is up to 15 lakhs, then there is
no option for more than that. The maximum is 15 lakhs,
so here you get a
benefit of only up to 10,000, I think I will have to
recheck, but you get a road ambulance up to 10,000.
And if
you talk about Optima Secure, then here
also you can get a
road ambulance up to the basic sum assured, let's say you have an insurance of 10 lakhs, then the
bill for 10 lakh road ambulance will
not come at all, it will only come to 5,000, 10,000, 15,000. So
here in all three you are getting the
right arrangement and the right benefit of road ambulance. If we
talk about air ambulance, then in Niva Bappa
you are getting a benefit of up to 5 lakhs,
in Ker Supreme it is 5 lakhs, but it is optional for
5 lakhs. If you get the air ambulance added, you have to pay
extra premium. Niva Bhop does
not have to pay extra premium, it
is inbuilt and in Optima Secure also you
get it inbuilt, no additional premium has to be paid, so
air ambulance is available occasionally like
Suppose there is some serious problem, then
you have to be transferred to a good hospital in another city through airjay, then the
expenses of air ambulance will
also be covered. Talking about consumer bill covers,
this feature was exposed a lot during Covid,
earlier people were not aware of it,
all such expenses, all such expenses which are
one-time use and throw in the hospital,
like PPE kit, gloves, mask,
these are one-time use and throw things, then
all those things are also covered in this, in
which this feature is known as Safeguard Plus in nb
and if you take this Safe Card
Plus feature, then
all the consumer bills listed in Annex 1, 2, 3, 4 are
completely covered.
Apart from this, if you have a
claim of up to ₹ lakh, then there will be no difference in the benefit you were getting from Booster Plus.
Thirdly, the inflation rate
is the inflation rate of India. According to CPI,
your additional insurance cover also increases by the same percentage as your inflation rate.
If you  If you buy Safeguard Plus as an optional
rider, you will have to pay an extra premium for it.
This is an optional
rider. It is also available as an option in Care Supreme.
Where the
name of consumer benefit is Claim Shield,
it means that if you are taking consumer benefit features,
only 68 items are covered there, whereas
in STFC Secure, you will get it inbuilt, for which
you do not have to pay a separate premium and
there this feature is known as Protect Benefit.
Talking about cover for organ donor, the
organ donor is also covered up to the sum amount as per
your insurance cover. For example, if someone's
kidney gets damaged and someone is donating an organ, then the
expenses incurred at that time are also covered
under the organ donor, so that benefit
up to the basic insurance cover and your
organ donor benefit will also be
covered in it.
Talking about assisting illness cover, if
someone already has a pre-existing illness and
purchases this policy.  There is a waiting period of three years in Niva Bappa, there is a
waiting period of four years in Supreme. There is a
waiting period of nine years in ADFC Optima Secure. If we
talk about any specific illness like
joint replacement,
hernia, all such
things, if there is a cataract operation, then it will be
covered after 24 months. There is an
alternative in all three policies. If you
also want to get AYUSH treatment done, then
AYUSH treatment is available for you in all three policies.
Talking about insurance cover, free
health checkup is available in Niva Bappa every
year and it is available up
to Rs. 10000 for every Rs. 10 lakh. If it becomes Rs. 10000 then
your sum assured will be up to Rs. 10000. You
can get a health checkup done. There
is also a free health checkup in Supreme but it
is optional. You can avail this feature by paying a separate premium.
You will
also get this feature in ADFC Optima Secure,
where it depends on the sum assured.
There is an insurance cover ranging from Rs. 5 lakh to Rs. 2 crore.
You
can get a health checkup done up to Rs 15,000 depending upon your
needs. Talking about consultation, unlimited
consultation is covered. In Niva Bupa, you
can consult a doctor over the phone. In Care
Supreme,
you can talk to a surgeon only. This will be the case with
unlimited consultation in Care Supreme.
And in Optima Secure, you
can get consultation related to 51 defined critical illnesses for free once per
insured person. Talking about shared accommodation,
suppose you go to the hospital and do
not take a single AC private room, but you take a
combined room for two people, then you
get some benefit. Both Bupa and STFC
give you Rs 800 per day,
you get a maximum of Rs 800. This is an
additional benefit; there is no need to pay a bill for it.
You get this benefit in shared accommodation.
Talking about room rent limit, it is a good thing that
room rent is included in all three plans.  There is
no limit, you
can get admitted in the hospital in the best room,
you will not have to pay any money from your pocket as per the room rent.
Talking about hospitalization, all the companies
available in the market
get the claim only on admission for 24 hours, but
Niva Bupa is
giving you benefit in the reassure plan even after admission for two hours.
Talking about basic sum, Niva
Bupa is providing you sum shed of Rs 5 lakh, 75 lakh, 10 lakh, 15 lakh, 20 lakh,
25 lakh, 50 lakh and up to 1 crore.
Talking about Care
Supreme, here you are taking insurance cover of Rs 5 lakh, 7 lakh, 10
lakh and 15 lakh with maximum up to 15 lakh.
Meaning, it is
not focusing on HN people,
its focus is
less on such people who need higher sum shed. It is giving maximum sum shed of up to 15 lakh,
whereas HDFC is giving cover of up to 2 crores as well.
Talking about discount on renewals,
if  You take care of your health, suppose you are
walking a thousand steps every day, everyone has
different conditions, I have
also explained that in a separate video of mine. You can see my videos on YouTube.
I have also made a separate video of this policy.
So when you
go for renewal, when your premium comes next year,
if you are a part of the Healthy and Fit and Wellness program, then
you get a discount of up to 30%.
This is inbuilt in the policy, for this you do
not have to pay any extra premium.
It is also available in Care under the name of Wellness,
but if you want to opt for this feature there, then
you will have to pay an additional premium.
In ADAC Optima Secure, this feature of
Wellness is not discounted on renewal,
but if you take a 2-year or 3-year
policy, then a discount of 75% or 10% is
available. In Family Floater, the
discount is
available in the first year, but at the
time of renewal,
discounts are not available in Optima Secure. Talking about
Annual Aggregate Deductible, this is an
excellent feature which very few people know about.
You can also utilize this,
like in Niva Buff, deductible up to 20000, 0000, 50000, 1 lakh has been given
and this again I have made a mistake, this
next deductible which I have
shown in Care Supreme is actually
not of Care Supreme, it is of Optima Secure,
so if you consider Optima Secure, if
you consider this option in Optima Secure, then
in Optima Secure you
can take deductible of 25000, 1
lakh, 2 lakh, 5 lakh in this manner, now what is this
deductible and what is the benefit from this, suppose let us say
you are getting
more premium, like I will give an example,
if you take a deductible of 3 lakh
in Optima Secure,
I am repeating again in Optima Secure,
here a mistake has happened in typing, so
if someone takes a deductible of 3 lakh in Optima Secure,
it means 3  If
you are not going to come to the company to claim till Rs. 1 lakh, then
you get a discount in premium till the age of 65,
then you can select  You
can, for example, have a 20% deductible in your Niva Bfam.
Often, people take a copay. It's much
better to purchase a deductible, which
is cheaper and provides excellent insurance cover.
Hospital cash
benefit is an optional benefit.
If you're admitted to a hospital,
you can get up to ₹1,000 per day,
depending on your situation.
Both these features are
available in both Rise and Gold.
These features are available in both Optima Secure and Optima Secure.
Personal accident benefit is up
to five times your health insurance coverage. You
can also take out a personal accident policy. This is also
optional. You
can purchase this in Niva B and ADAC by paying an additional premium.
ICU cover has
no limit, unlike room rates. This is a
great option.
You can avail the full benefit up to the sum assured at the time
of policy entry.  This is what
I am telling you at the end, so an
adult of 18 years can purchase the policy, if there
is a child then a child of 90 days can
purchase this policy, all three are
in the policy and the adult can purchase this policy till life long,
if the child is 24 years old in Care Supreme
then they will have to be separated,
in Tama Secure if the child turns 25 then they will have to
take a separate policy and
in Niva Bupa a child up to 30 years can also be a
part of the family floater, after that
they will also have to take a separate policy, so I
hope you liked this video,
you must have liked this comparison, there may be some typing error at one or two
places, please
ignore it a little
and compare, if you purchase the policy after comparing
then definitely you will get more
benefit, thank you so much for watching the
video